A lot of us are overwhelmed, pissed, and scared.
I don't want to wait till the next election.
I don't want to just write my congressperson and hope that they'll do the right thing.
I don't want to just post things to the vacuum of social media.
I don't want to just make statements about things.
I want to change how things are.
There are a zillion things we can do, and people are coming up with new ones all the time.
This video is going to focus on mutual aid projects, what they are, and why we should be developing them right now.
Mutual aid projects are a form of political participation in which people take responsibility for caring for one another and changing political conditions.
Not just through symbolic acts or putting pressure on their representatives and government, but by actually building new social relations that are more survivable.
During recent flooding and storms, we saw mutual aid in action as people helped each other survive.
Mutual aid isn't just for those big-weather disasters.
It is also for the daily, routine, life-threatening disasters of capitalism and white supremacy.
People who are pissed about police in prisons are doing mutual aid work like creating prison letter-writing projects,
where people get connected to pen pals in prison to build relationships,
help prepare for release, help prisoners have advocates on the outside,
and help build a movement against policing in prisons that is informed and led by the people who know the very most about how the system actually works.
Some people are creating jail support programs,
where people get together to make a schedule and agree to be outside their local jail on that schedule
and greet anyone getting out and help them get what they need.
Maybe a ride, clothes, a phone to call contacts, information about services or benefits.
Some people are organizing community bail funds,
revolving funds that can pay people's bail so that they are not locked up while they try to prepare for their defense.
Money bail systems are one of the ways that poor people and people of color are given the worst chances in the criminal system.
Court support projects are where people coordinate to accompany someone facing charges to their court dates,
ideally by packing the court with supporters each time so that no one has to go alone,
and sometimes to influence lawyers, judges, and jury by showing their support for the criminalized person.
Some people are coordinating ride systems to help families visit prisoners who are being held in facilities far from home.
In Oakland, the Oakland Power Projects are about strengthening people's skills to respond to community emergencies
in ways that minimize police contact.
When you call 911 for a health emergency, the cops come too, and that often leads to violence.
The Oakland Power Projects is about training the community to respond to health emergencies,
including mental health crises, chronic health problems, and acute health emergencies,
so that people don't have to call 911.
People who are scared about the emboldenment of ICE and Border Patrol and increasing deportations
are doing things like forming rapid response networks,
where people warn each other about immigration raids and help each other hide,
and helping immigrants do safety planning in case they get detained
so that someone is ready to take care of their kids and elders.
Some rapid response projects are even working on training people to show up
and physically stop ICE from taking someone away.
Imagine if we built that kind of power to stop arrests through rapid mobilization
of a lot of people to outnumber cops.
No More Deaths, an organization in Arizona, works to save the lives of people crossing the border
by putting food, water, and supplies in the harsh desert areas
where people who are crossing often die from the conditions.
There are so many mutual aid project possibilities
because there are so many intense ways people aren't having their needs met
in the brutal systems we live under.
Like food projects like Food Not Bombs,
projects where people organize temporary housing for people coming out of prison or foster care
by opening their homes to each other,
childcare collectives where people watch each other's kids
so they can go to political meetings, court, or jobs,
projects where people accompany vulnerable people like trans people
or people with disabilities to medical appointments
or public benefits offices and hearings,
projects where people make sure neighbors being pushed out by gentrification
have good access to information about their housing rights
and accompany each other to housing court,
help people read documents and defend themselves from eviction,
projects where people protest landlords who are refusing to make repairs
or give back security deposits
by directly protesting at those landlords' houses and businesses.
The messages of this work are
the government is fixed, we can't rely on it.
You are not alone.
The system is the problem, not the person being targeted by it.
And we're going to take matters into our own hands
and help each other survive right now
rather than expecting help from the same systems
that have a clear history of causing harm.
Mutual aid projects don't just help with the current disasters,
they help us prepare for the ongoing disasters
that are emerging because of climate chaos and crumbling infrastructure.
When we build cooperative projects,
practice making decisions together,
share things,
meet more people in our communities
and learn about each other's skills and needs
and learn how current systems work
and how they are not working,
we're better prepared for the next storm,
the next blackout,
and the next budget cuts.
Something really important about all this
is that mutual aid is not charity.
Charity is where rich people and institutions
give tiny crumbs to poor people
to make themselves look better.
Usually there are a lot of strings attached to what they give,
like giving only to mothers or only to children,
only to sober people or only to people of faith.
Charity rides on the idea that rich people
or social workers should decide
who is the deserving poor
and who is the undeserving poor,
and that rich people can put conditions
on the housing or food or cash they give poor people.
Charity blames poor people for poverty.
Mutual aid blames the system for making people poor
and says everyone deserves everything they need.
Charity affirms the existing distribution
of wealth and life chances.
Mutual aid challenges it.
Charity is top-down.
Mutual aid is horizontal.
Charity is about control, hierarchy, and isolation.
Mutual aid is about solidarity,
liberation, and participation.
People are scared and angry right now
and trying to find ways to fight back
and support each other.
Building mutual aid projects
is a way to plug people in,
build shared understandings of current conditions,
offer meaningful support to vulnerable people,
and prepare for the coming disasters.
Mutual aid work is not easy.
It means forming lasting commitments
to doing hard work,
collaborating with people
even when we have conflict,
and facing the heart-wrenching realities
of the systems we live under.
It is also deeply satisfying work
that transforms us
from being exasperated, passive observers
of the shitstorm we're living in
to inspired builders of the new world
we desperately crave in need.
Stop believing in authority
and start believing in each other.
We're all we've got,
we're all we need.
We're all we need.